Guide to the Herman Haupt Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Herman Haupt papers
1800-1984
MS 269
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
10
(23 boxes)
The papers consist of Herman Haupt's business and personal correspondence, financial and legal papers, and writings, which were collected by Herman Haupt Chapman during his research on his grandfather's life. In addition, the papers include the manuscript of Chapman's unpublished biography, as well as transcripts of documents, photographs, additional family correspondence, diaries, and other family papers, and Chapman's own correspondence files which relate to his research and biographical writings. The papers highlight Haupt's career as a civil engineer, particularly his work on the Hoosac Tunnel and his subsequent legal contests with the Commonwealth of Massachusetts and his service to the Union during the Civil War.
Haupt, Herman, 1817-1905
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Herman Haupt Chapman, 1957-1959; Mrs. Herman Haupt Chapman, 1964; and others, 1974-1984.
Existence and Location of Copies
Journal of Anna Cecilia Keller Haupt is available on microfilm (52 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM56.
Associated Materials
Related material: Herman Haupt Chapman Papers (MS 134), (Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.)
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: Correspondence, 1800-1960. II. Personal Papers, 1840-1955. III. Herman Haupt Chapman Files, 1845-1984.
Scope and Contents
The Herman Haupt Papers consist of business and personal correspondence, financial and legal papers, and writings of Herman Haupt, which were collected by Herman Haupt Chapman during his research on his grandfather's life. In addition the papers include the manuscript of Chapman's unpublished biography, as well as transcripts of documents, photographs, additional family correspondence, diaries, other family papers, and Chapman's own correspondence files which relate to his research and biographical writings. The papers highlight Haupt's career as a civil engineer, particularly his work on the Hoosac Tunnel and his subsequent legal contests with the Commonwealth of Massachusetts and his service to the Union during the Civil War.
Herman Haupt Chapman and his wife donated the bulk of the material to the Yale Library between 1957 and 1964. A few additional items were added to the papers between 1974 and 1980. Additional papers concerning Herman Haupt Chapman's career as a member of the Yale School of Forestry faculty are located in the Herman Haupt Chapman Papers (MS 134). The Haupt Papers are arranged in three series: I. CORRESPONDENCE, 1800-1960; II. PERSONAL PAPERS, 1840-1955; and III. HERMAN HAUPT CHAPMAN FILES, 1845-1984.
Series I includes correspondence and other papers of Haupt, Chapman, and other family members, while Series II is composed mainly of Haupt's legal and financial papers. Series III contains Chapman's manuscript, notes, and other research material gathered for a projected biography of Herman Haupt. In quantity the papers are nearly equally divided between those of Haupt and his contemporaries and those relating to Chapman's research and writing.
Series I includes correspondence and other papers of several members of the Haupt family as well as transcripts of material copied by Herman Haupt Chapman, which are scattered throughout the series and concentrated in box 10. The series, which is arranged in chronological order, begins with business correspondence and papers of Haupt's father, John Jacob Houpt, a merchant in Philadelphia. Material of Herman Haupt begins in folder 3 and a diary of his wife Anna Cecilia Keller Haupt is in folder 4. This diary, which dates from 1842 to 1843, describes family life in Gettysburg, Pennsylvania where Herman Haupt was serving as principal of the Oakridge Select Academy. The diary is also available on microfilm (HM 56). During periods of separation Herman Haupt wrote to his wife and provided descriptions of his work, addressing her as "dear Sis". Some letters after 1847 relate to Haupt's work as an assistant to J. Edgar Thomson on the Pennsylvania Railroad.
The files become increasingly more abundant and substantive after the commencement of Haupt's work for the Troy and Greenfield Railroad on the Hoosac Tunnel in 1856. The files include agreements, resolutions, and acts of the Commonwealth of Massachusetts, as well as correspondence with financial supporters and creditors such as Henry Cartwright, William A. Galbraith, Henry D. Steever, Samuel Lane, and Edward W. Serrell. The correspondence relates more to Haupt's financial problems and less to tunnel engineering. There are also exchanges with Haupt and Keller family members in Pennsylvania. Letterpress copybooks (folders 173-174) contain copies of Haupt's outgoing letters concerning work on the tunnel.
The state of Massachusetts took over the work on the tunnel in 1862, at about the same time that Haupt joined the staff of General Irvin McDowell. Haupt's letters to his wife and family in Cambridge, Massachusetts describe his activities. The files at this point also contain transcripts of correspondence and documents located in other repositories, relating to Haupt's Civil War service, particularly Haupt's role in the Gettysburg victory. Files after Haupt's return to Massachusetts in 1863 focus on Haupt's continuing legal battles with the Commonwealth of Massachusetts for payment of debts incurred on the Hoosac Tunnel. During the winter of 1866 there are almost daily letters to Anna Cecilia Haupt concerning hearings on the matter.
Folder 74 contains another piece of Anna Cecilia Haupt's diary, which details a trip to England and Scotland during which Herman Haupt delivered a paper on the application of machinery to tunnelling. A copy of the paper is in folder 75. Correspondence in the 1870s documents Haupt's new business ventures in Virginia. The purchase and work of the Old Dominion Granite Company is discussed in exchanges with Thomas Ackley and son Lewis Muhlenberg Haupt, while the operation of a resort in Giles County, Virginia at Mt. Lake is the subject of family correspondence. The files also contain references to Haupt's work on the Piedmont Air Line Railway.
Files in the 1880s, containing affidavits, resolutions, claims, articles of agreement, and correspondence, mainly document the negotiations to reach a final settlement with the state of Massachusetts. The files contain much less detail on Haupt's activities for the last twenty-five years of his life. There is some correspondence with Edward Appleton and Robert Lenox Belknap concerning Haupt's employment by the Northern Pacific Railroad and exchanges with Frank Woodman concerning the Mt. Lake Land Company. After 1900 files concern Haupt's investments in the National Nutrient Company, which had perfected a process for producing powdered milk.
Files after Haupt's death in December, 1905 contain records kept by Lewis M. Haupt as executor of his father's estate. By the mid 1920s the correspondence is mainly that of Herman Haupt Chapman and concerns the Haupt family and his research on Herman Haupt. There is correspondence with the fledgling Colonial Haupt Association. Letters from Ethel M. Hughes and Florence H. Urren concern Chapman's research and manuscript, while correspondence with several historians and editors relates to Chapman's interest in publishing his research. Several librarians write to acknowledge receiving copies of Chapman's typescript of the "Unpublished Correspondence of Brigadier General Herman Haupt, July 1861-Septebmer 1862".
Series II contains numerous financial and legal documents such as agreements, testimony, affidavits, minutes, exhibits, contracts, payment schedules, patents and accounts relating to Haupt's work on the Hoosac Tunnel. There are also smaller but similar files for Haupt's involvement with the National Nutrient Company. Folders [illegible]217-218 contain photostats of circulars issued by Haupt as general manager of the Northern Pacific Railroad. The series also includes a diary and school notebook kept by Haupt's seventeen year old sister Mary E. Haupt while teaching school in Gettysburg and studying in Philadelphia. Among the legal documents in box 12 is a copy of Anna Cecilia Haupt's will detailing her philanthropic bequests and her charitable interests in Giles County, Virginia.
Series III contains the manuscript for Herman Haupt Chapman's biography of his grandfather and typed transcripts of documents made for his research. The transcripts exist in multiple copies and are arranged chronologically and by topic. Photographs (or photostats) and print negatives of documents, Haupt, family members, residences, railroads, bridges, and tunnels are found in folders 331-348. There are only a few original photographs among them. Material in folders 349-381 was integrated into folders 331-348.
Folders 382-401 include additional resource material on Herman Haupt's life. They contain catalogues from the schools at which Haupt taught, Haupt's books and articles on engineering, steam heating, river improvements, compressed air, politics, and power transmission, and reports concerning the Pennsylvania Transportation Company pipeline and the Old Dominion Granite Company. Folders 289-291 contain a manuscript of Haupt's reminiscences of his Civil War experiences. Folders at the end of the series also include family histories, memorabilia, and additional transcripts by Herman Haupt Chapman.
Biographical / Historical
Herman Haupt was born in Philadelphia in 1817 and graduated from the United States Military Academy in 1835. He resigned his commission to become a civil engineer. He was employed by the Pennsylvania Railroad and in 1856 undertook work on the Hoosac Tunnel for the Troy and Greenfield Railroad in Massachusetts. From 1862 to 1863 he served as chief of construction and transportation on the United States military railroads and retired with the rank of brigadier-general of volunteers. In 1876 he undertook construction of an oil pipeline for the Pennsylvania Tranportation Company. From 1881 until 1884 he served as general manager of the Northern Pacific Railroad, was president of General Compressed Air and Power Company from 1892 to 1905, and was president of the National Nutrient Company from 1899 until his death in 1905.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boring machinery; Engineering; Railroad tunnels -- Massachusetts; Railroads -- United States; Gettysburg (Pa.); Hoosac Tunnel (Mass.); Mountain Lake (Va.); United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Transportation; Diaries; Patents (license); Civil engineers; Ackley, Thomas W.; Appleton, Edward; Belknap, Robert Lenox, 1848-1896; Cartwright, Henry; Chapman, Herman Haupt, 1874-1963; Galbraith, William A.; Griswold, John Augustus, 1822-1872; Haupt, Ann Cecelia, 1821-1891; Haupt, Herman, 1817-1905; Haupt, John Jacob, 1776-1828; Haupt, Lewis M. (Lewis Muhlenberg), 1844-1937; Haupt, Mary Elizabeth, 1828-; Hughes, Ethel Mary, 1875-; Keller, Benjamin, 1794-1864; Lane, Samuel M.; McDowell, Irvin, 1818-1885; Steever, Henry D.; Thomson, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1808-1874; Urner, Florence H.; Woodman, Frank; Colonial Haupt Association; National Nutrient Co; Northern Pacific Railway Company; Old Dominion Granite Co; Troy and Greenfield Railroad Company
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1800-1960; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in chronological order. Letterpress copybooks and transcripts are filed at the end of the series.
  - 1800 - 1859 March (Box 1, Folder 1-20)
  - 1859 April - 1862 (Box 2, Folder 21-42)
  - 1863 - 1866 April (Box 3, Folder 43-64)
  - 1866 May - 1876 (Box 4, Folder 65-86)
  - 1877 - 1885 July (Box 5, Folder 87-108)
  - 1885 August - 1907 December (Box 6, Folder 109-134)
  - 1908 - 1956 (Box 7, Folder 135-160)
  - 1957 - 1960, undated (Box 8, Folder 161-172)
  - Letterpress copybooks, 1861-1967 (Box 9, Folder 173-174)
  - Typescripts, [ca. 1950s] (Box 10, Folder 175-189)
- PERSONAL PAPERS, 1840-1955; Series II
  This series is arranged alphabetically by record type.
  - Business papers, 1856-1898, undated (Box 11, Folder 190-193)
    General note
    See also: box 23
  - Contracts, 1854-1884, undated (Box 11, Folder 194-196)
  - Financial papers, 1840-1910, undated (Box 11, Folder 197-210)
  - Legal documents, 1888-1955, undated (Box 12, Folder 211)
  - Memoranda book, 1860-1865 (Box 12, Folder 212)
  - Statements by Haupt, undated (Box 12, Folder 213)
  - Topical files
    - National Nutrient Company, 1895-1916, undated (Box 12, Folder 214-216)
    - Northern Pacific Railroad, 1881-1883, undated (Box 12, Folder 217-218)
  - Volumes
    - Diary: Mary E. Haupt, 1846-1847 (Box 12, Folder 219)
    - Ledger, 1856-1861 (Box 12, Folder 220)
- HERMAN HAUPT CHAPMAN FILES, 1845-1984; Series III
  This series is arranged by topic or record type.
  - The Complete Biography of General Haupt, [ca. 1950s] (Box 13, Folder 221-240)
  - The Complete Biography of General Haupt, [ca. 1950s] (Box 14, Folder 241-248)
  - Chronological notes, 1817-1863, [ca. 1950s] (Box 14, Folder 249-255)
  - Chronological notes, 1864-1889, [ca. 1950s] (Box 15, Folder 256-269)
  - Civil War, [ca. 1950s] (Box 16, Folder 270-291)
  - Haupt family records, [ca. 1950s] (Box 17, Folder 292-295)
  - Hoosac Tunnel, [ca. 1950s] (Box 17, Folder 296-309)
  - Hoosac Tunnel, [ca. 1950s] (Box 18, Folder 310-323)
  - Hoosac Tunnel, [ca. 1950s] (Box 19, Folder 324-330)
  - Photographs
    - Haupt, Herman, 1863-1899, undated (Box 20, Folder 331)
    - Haupt family members, 1848, 1852, 1905, undated (Box 20, Folder 332-333)
    - Haupt family burial plots, Circa 1890, undated (Box 20, Folder 334)
    - Haupt family residences, 1974, undated (Box 20, Folder 335)
    - Haupt medals and memorials, 1867, undated (Box 20, Folder 336)
    - Haupt projects
      - Civil War, Circa 1863 (Box 20, Folder 337-338)
      - Diagrams and drawings, undated (Box 20, Folder 339-340)
      - Railroad, 1863, 1954, undated (Box 20, Folder 341-342)
    - Individuals, A - M, undated (Box 21, Folder 343)
    - Letters and certificates, 1852-1897, undated (Box 21, Folder 344)
    - Mountain Lake Hotel and environs, Mountain Lake, Va., 1915, undated (Box 21, Folder 345)
    - Printed material, 1857, 1866 (Box 21, Folder 346)
    - Railroad maps, undated (Box 21, Folder 347)
    - Railroad-related cartoon drawings, undated (Box 21, Folder 348)
  - Printed material, 1845-1867 (Box 21, Folder 382-385)
  - Printed material, 1870-1984, undated (Box 22, Folder 386-396)
  - Miscellanea (Box 22, Folder 397-403)
- OVERSIZE
  - Patents, land records, 1853-1872 (Box 23)